Think of a leader who you admire and
respect.
What qualities do they have
that makes them a good leader?
Maybe they're an active listener.
Maybe they're great at fostering a sense
of community for people around them.
As a project manager,
leadership is a big part of the job.
But being a great project manager is
about more than simply leading a team to
complete a project.
It's about supporting the people on
your team to do their best work, and
enabling people to build
things they're proud of.
In this video, we'll define teamwork and
explain why it's important for
successful project management.
The best leaders are able to
get people to work together.
That's why a project manager's
ability to develop and
lead teams that work well together is so
important.
But before we go further, let's pause and
consider, what exactly is a team?
Though there are many different
definitions of the word team,
here's how we describe it here at Google.
A team is a group of people who plan,
solve problems, make decisions, and
review progress in service of
a specific project, or objective.
Team members rely on each
other to get things done.
For example, a software engineering
team might be tasked with creating one
seamless software experience
that meets users needs.
Beyond coordinating with the project
manager members of the software
engineering team will also coordinate with
one another as they work toward their
shared goal.
Teams differ from workgroups,
which we define as being based on
organizational or managerial hierarchy.
Though people within a workgroup might
be working toward a common goal,
their work is more likely to
be coordinated, controlled or
assigned by single person or entity.
For example, a workgroup focused on
quality assurance testing might be
tasked with running a set of test plans.
The group manager might
split up that work and
assign each quality assurance
tester a plan to review.
But unlike a team,
the testers will work independently of
one another to complete their tasks.
And will coordinate mainly
with the manager and
the development team of
the feature they're testing.
Teams and work groups each have unique
benefits within a larger organization.
But for the purpose of this program,
we'll focus on teams.
More specifically, we'll discuss
how project managers develop and
lead effective teams by
fostering a culture of teamwork.
Teamwork is an effective
collaborative way of working in which
each person is committed to and
heading toward a shared goal.
Teamwork maximizes the individual
strength of each team member to
bring out the best in each person.
As you might imagine,
teamwork is a crucial part of
successful project management.
There are a few reasons for this.
For one, teamwork fosters creativity.
A team might leverage the diverse
perspectives, skills and
experiences of their members
to devise better solutions and
build products that address more diverse
user needs than they might have if they
were working independently of each other.
Teamwork also encourages accountability.
The knowledge that the execution of
your tasks directly impacts the tasks of
the rest of the team can
be a powerful motivator.
And most importantly,
teamwork helps you get stuff done.
Big complex projects need smart,
capable people to complete tasks and
to reach milestones to
meet the project goals.
As the project manager, it's your job to
encourage others to actively engage in
working together as a team to foster
creativity, encourage accountability and
to get stuff done.
Teamwork is an effective collaborative
way of working and when done right,
it can positively impact both measurable
team results and the team culture.
Coming up, we'll take you through
the elements of effective teams.
Meet you there.